{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "This man’s efforts at social climbing included buying Hughenden Manor and marrying the widow of Wyndham Lewis. After Robert Peel denied this man a cabinet seat, he became the leader of the Young England group. As prime minister, this author of the novels Coningsby and Vivian Grey introduced a bill to make Queen Victoria “Empress of India.” This Conservative was the rival of William Gladstone. For 10 points, name this prime minister of Jewish descent.",
      "answer": "Benjamin Disraeli <SH> {I}"
    },
    {
      "question": "The Daily Mirror claimed Zaharie Shah, an employee of one of these businesses, had a suspicious computer program. One of these businesses has headquarters at a location named for Sultan Abdul Aziz Shah in Subang. An employee of one of these businesses searched for information about \"doors and their security provisions\" before committing suicide by crashing into a mountain. For 10 points, name this kind of company exemplified by Germanwings.",
      "answer": "airlines <MC> {I}"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man's longtime assistant and heir was Clyde Tolson. This man claimed personal responsibility for the downfall of Alvin \"Creepy\" Karpis. After he died in 1972, his personal files containing incriminating information on many Presidents were destroyed. In 1956, this man's organization began the CO-INTELPRO program that targeted Communists and Black Panthers. For 10 points, name this first Director of the Federal Bureau of Investigation.",
      "answer": "John Edgar Hoover <MC> {I}"
    },
    {
      "question": "The Trinovantes were recruited by this person to help battle an army led by Petillius Cerialis. This leader destroyed the city of Camulodunum before being defeated by Gaius Suetonius Paulinus. The leader of the Iceni people, this person was married to Prasutagus until he died, after which she led an army to crush the Roman Ninth Legion. For 10 points, name this Celtic queen who rose up against Roman rule in 60 AD.",
      "answer": "Boudicca <VP> {I}"
    },
    {
      "question": "This work’s third chapter claims that German philosophers saw the French Revolution as “true human Will.” This work’s second chapter calls for “Free education for all children in public schools” after calling for “Abolition of the family!” It begins “A specter is haunting Europe,” and claims that “the history of all hitherto existing society is the history of class struggles.” For 10 points, name this 1848 pamphlet co-authored by Friedrich Engels and Karl Marx.",
      "answer": "The Communist Manifesto <SH> {I} 2015 National History Bowl High School Championships Round 5"
    },
    {
      "question": "Book 2 of Herodotus's Histories notes that \"other spices except frankincense\" were used during this process. The object central to this process is dried with natron for seventy days. This process uses four canopic jars that represent the cardinal directions. The brain was removed through the nose during this process, which also requires wrapping the body with long strands of linen. For 10 points, identify this process used by Ancient Egyptians to preserve the dead.",
      "answer": "Egyptian mummification <KG> {I}"
    },
    {
      "question": "This composer’s namesake songbook features a ballad which asks “all goodly sport, for my comfort, who shall me let?” This composer of “Pastime With Good Company” employed choirmaster William Cornish, and his daughter gave Thomas Tallis a monopoly on music printing. According to popular legend, he wrote “Greensleeves” for his second wife. For 10 points, name this composer and English monarch who married and beheaded Anne Boleyn.",
      "answer": "King Henry VIII <CW> {I}"
    },
    {
      "question": "Joseph Pulitzer offered a reward for information about this man's huckster father, Bill. This man's estate is named for the Dutch word for \"lookout\" and is named Kykuit (pr. KIE-quit). Along with Henry Flagler and several investors, he led the \"Cleveland Conquest\" to take out business competitors. This man referred to company critic and muckraker Ida Tarbell as \"Miss Tarbarrel.\" For 10 points, name this patriarch of a wealthy family who founded the Standard Oil Company.",
      "answer": "John Davison Rockefeller Sr. <MC> {I} 2015 National History Bowl High School Championships Round 5"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This initiative directly caused the formation of Lake Chagan. This project conducted tests at an area known as the \"Polygon.\" The \"Third Idea\" of this program was largely derived from a rival program's Teller-Ulam configuration. This program benefited greatly from information provided by Klaus Fuchs and the Rosenbergs. For 10 points, identify this project that produced Tsar Bomba, whose detonation produced the strongest man-made explosion in history.",
        "answer": "Soviet nuclear program"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What activist and former worker for the Soviet atomic program is the namesake of a prize handed out by the European Union \"for Freedom of Thought\"?",
        "answer": "Andrei Dmitrievich Sakharov <KG> {I}"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This poem was believed to be a history until a fire in the Cotton library led to a second look at the Nowell Codex. Clues to the proper date range of its composition include a raid on the Frisians and frequent references to \"Geats\" and \"Geatland\" in what's now Sweden. In this poem, attacks on the mead hall of Heorot lead to a plea for aid from King Hrothgar. For 10 points, name this poem in which a dragon and the monster Grendel are slain by the title hero, an Old English epic.",
        "answer": "Beowulf <MJ>"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Old English literature also includes a translation attributed to Alfred the Great of what Latin dialogue by Boethius (pr. boe-EE-thee-us), which Ignatius J. Reilly adores in A Confederacy of Dunces?",
        "answer": "The Consolation of Philosophy <MJ> {I}"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man competed in the North Channel Naval Duel against the Drake while commanding the Ranger. After being denied command of the America, this native Scot entered the service of Catherine the Great. In a battle against the Countess of Scarborough and Serapis, this man exclaimed, “I have not yet begun to fight!” For 10 points, name this captain of the Bonhomme Richard, a naval hero of the American Revolution.",
        "answer": "John Paul Jones"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What ship is located in Charlestown Harbor, is the world’s oldest commissioned warship afloat, and is nicknamed “Old Ironsides”?",
        "answer": "USS Constitution <ED> {I}"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This dynasty won the battle of Tolbiac against the Alemanni. Fredegar claims that the kings of this dynasty descended from a mythical sea creature called the Quinotaur. Much of the history of this dynasty survives only through the writing of Gregory of Tours. This dynasty ended when Pope Zachary deposed Childeric III. Saint Remigius baptized this dynasty’s founder Clovis I. For 10 points, name this Frankish dynasty that preceded the Carolingian dynasty.",
        "answer": "Merovingian Dynasty"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Childeric III suffered what fate, which involves the cutting of all the hair on the scalp as a sign of humility?",
        "answer": "he was tonsured <CKM> {I} 2015 National History Bowl High School Championships Round 5"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Charles Lightoller threatened some people trying to leave from this event because they weren't English. During this event, a band is said to have played \"Nearer, My God, to Thee.\" J. Bruce Ismay controversially fled this event early, while Margaret Brown stayed to help. This disaster for the White Star Line occurred despite warnings from the SS Californian about dangerous icebergs. For 10 points, identify this 1912 event in which a supposedly unsinkable ship capsized.",
        "answer": "sinking of the RMS Titanic"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What businessman was the richest person aboard the Titanic, but died as a result of Lightoller's insistence that only women and children board the lifeboats?",
        "answer": "John Jacob Astor IV <KG> {I}"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This leader is cast as a \"Jacobin\" in a history by C. L. R. James. This man became the most prominent leader of an event which began after a ceremony at Bois Caiman conducted by Dutty Boukman. This man fought the War of Knives with Andre Rigaud, and he was eventually captured by Charles Leclerc. This man's officers included future emperors Henri-Christophe and Jean-Jacques Dessalines. For 10 points, name this leader of the Haitian Revolution.",
        "answer": "Toussaint L'Ouverture"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What disease killed many French soldiers during the Haitian Revolution and was later investigated by Walter Reed?",
        "answer": "yellow fever <JB> {I}"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man was opposed by “Snow White and the six dwarfs” and was nicknamed “Pepsi-Cola kid.” Millard Tydings investigated this man’s claims, which sparked Margaret Chase Smith’s “Declaration of Conscience” speech. This person was finally brought down after Joseph Welch asked him if he had “no sense of decency” during hearings with the U.S. Army. For 10 points, name this man nicknamed “Tail Gunner,” a Senator who helped fuel the Red Scare in the 1950s.",
        "answer": "Joseph McCarthy"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "McCarthy was supported by Joseph, the scion of what Massachusetts family, which had another member later become President?",
        "answer": "Kennedy <JZ> {I}"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The winner of the 2012 Arthur Ashe Courage Award, this coach was named the Naismith Coach of the Century in 2000. Candace Parker made a landmark slam dunk while playing for this coach, who was diagnosed with early-onset Alzheimer's disease in 2011. For 10 points, name this longtime coach of the University of Tennessee women’s basketball team who is the winningest coach in the history of NCAA basketball.",
        "answer": "Pat Summitt"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Which university’s women’s basketball program based in the city of Storrs is coached by Geno Auriemma and has been a major rival of the University of Tennessee?",
        "answer": "University of Connecticut <ED> {I} 2015 National History Bowl High School Championships Round 5"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "AMERICA IN 1919,",
      "prompt": "In 1919, the United States…",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Had completed fighting in what war the previous year?",
          "answer": "World War I"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was led by what Democratic President?",
          "answer": "Woodrow Wilson"
        },
        {
          "question": "Saw a man named Edsel take over what company from his father?",
          "answer": "Ford Motor Company"
        },
        {
          "question": "Approved what amendment guaranteeing women's suffrage?",
          "answer": "Nineteenth Amendment"
        },
        {
          "question": "Featured what anti-Communist take over as Attorney General?",
          "answer": "Alexander Mitchell Palmer"
        },
        {
          "question": "Experienced a massive race riot in July in what Midwestern city?",
          "answer": "Chicago, Illinois"
        },
        {
          "question": "Experienced a disaster in which this substance burst out of a tank in Boston?",
          "answer": "Molasses"
        },
        {
          "question": "Witnessed a five-day general strike in February in what western city?",
          "answer": "Seattle <MC> {I}"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "AZTECS",
      "prompt": "Name the aztecs...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Were based in Tenochtitlan, which is now the location of which city?",
          "answer": "Mexico City"
        },
        {
          "question": "Were conquered by forces led by which Spaniard?",
          "answer": "Hernan Cortes"
        },
        {
          "question": "Were ruled by which emperor who was killed during the Spanish conquest?",
          "answer": "Moctezuma II"
        },
        {
          "question": "Worshipped Tlaloc, a deity of what natural phenomenon?",
          "answer": "rain"
        },
        {
          "question": "Created an empire made up of how many city-states?",
          "answer": "three"
        },
        {
          "question": "Worshipped which god of war, the patron deity of Tenochtitlan?",
          "answer": "Huitzilopochtli be reasonably lenient with pronunciation"
        },
        {
          "question": "Mainly spoke which language, which is still in use today?",
          "answer": "Nahuatl"
        },
        {
          "question": "Were studied by Bernardino de Sahagun, who wrote which manuscript about them?",
          "answer": "Florentine Codex <TR> {I}"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "HISTORY OF FOOD",
      "prompt": "What…",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Crop was cultivated by the Greeks to make “virgin oil?”",
          "answer": "olives"
        },
        {
          "question": "Plant, sometimes called maize, was extensively cultivated by the Aztecs?",
          "answer": "corn"
        },
        {
          "question": "Country suffered a massive potato famine in the 19th century?",
          "answer": "Republic of Ireland"
        },
        {
          "question": "Capital of Aquitaine is the major source of French red wine?",
          "answer": "Bordeaux"
        },
        {
          "question": "Largest German state by area developed Weisswurst, or white sausage?",
          "answer": "Bavaria"
        },
        {
          "question": "Durable food made from water, flour, and salt was often eaten by Civil war troops?",
          "answer": "hardtack"
        },
        {
          "question": "Narragansett dish is made from lima beans and corn?",
          "answer": "succotash"
        },
        {
          "question": "Food was fermented to make garum, an ancient delicacy?",
          "answer": "fish <Ike> {I}"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Members of this party include a governor who ordered the burning of railroad bridges leading to Baltimore. Thomas Holliday Hicks was a member of this party, which was formed from the Order of the Star-Spangled (20 pts)",
        "Banner. Millard Fillmore carried only Maryland as its 1856 Presidential candidate. This party advocated for a 25-year (10 pts)",
        "residency requirement for citizenship as part of its nativist platform. For 10 points, what anti- Catholic and anti-immigrant third party took its colloquial name from its members' responses when asked about its activities?"
      ],
      "answer": "Know-Nothing Party <DW> {I}"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Independently of James Lind, this man discovered that sauerkraut could prevent scurvy. This man replaced Alexander Dalrymple as the leader of a voyage to observe a transit of Venus. During that voyage, this man stopped in \"Stingray (20 pts)",
        "Harbor,\" where Daniel Solander and Joseph Banks collected so many species that it was renamed (10 pts)",
        "\"Botany Bay.\" This commander of the Endeavor proved that New Zealand was composed of two islands. For 10 points, name this British explorer whose three eighteenth-century voyages mapped much of the Pacific Ocean."
      ],
      "answer": "James Cook <DW> {I}"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man joked \"Well, God has arrived\" when his friend Ludwig Wittgenstein came to teach at his university. This philandering husband of dancer Lydia Lopokova, a non- philosopher who discussed philosophy with the Bloomsbury Group, proposed the underlying assumptions that Alvin (20 pts)",
        "Hansen used to make the IS/LM model. This man argued that demands for heavy reparations would cripple (10 pts)",
        "Germany's economy in The Economic Consequences of the Peace. For 10 points, name this Cambridge economist whose General Theory argued for government deficit spending during recessions."
      ],
      "answer": "John Maynard Keynes <MJ> {I}"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) According to lore, a cannonball attacking this institution went right through a portrait of George II. A siege during the American Revolution damaged this place's Nassau Hall in January 1777. Theologian Jonathan Edwards briefly served as president of this (20 pts)",
        "institution while it was still named merely for the state it's located in. This school traded a cannon back and forth with its historic rival (10 pts)",
        "Rutgers in the 19th century, before its dining societies developed into the current \"eating clubs.\" For 10 points, name this Ivy League university located in New Jersey."
      ],
      "answer": "Princeton University <MJ> {I} 2015 National History Bowl High School Championships Round 5"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One ruler of this name was replaced by Amadeo I after abdicating. A ruler of this name abdicated after losing the Battle of Alcolea to Juan Prim and Francisco Serrano. That ruler succeeded her father Ferdinand VII and fought supporters of her (20 pts)",
        "uncle in the Carlist Wars. Another queen with this name forced the surrender of Muhammad XII and united the (10 pts)",
        "crowns of Castile and Aragon through marriage. For 10 points, give this name common to two Spanish queens, the first of whom completed the Reconquista along with her husband Ferdinand."
      ],
      "answer": "Isabella <TR> {I}"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This leader's police opened fire on protesters at the Turkman Gate in an incident investigated by the Shah Commission. Slogans such as \"Elect a Government That Works\" and \"Eradicate Poverty!\" were used by this leader with a lifelong white streak of (20 pts)",
        "hair. This leader put a relative in charge of a slum clearance and forced sterilization program, ruled by decree during the Emergency period, and ordered Operation (10 pts)",
        "Blue Star, a raid on the Golden Temple. For 10 points, name this Prime Minister of India who was assassinated by Sikh bodyguards, the daughter of Jawaharlal Nehru."
      ],
      "answer": "Indira Gandhi <JB> {I}"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "Cecil Morgan aided a \"squad\" named for this substance which aimed to impeach populist governor Huey Long. A reaction involving this substance destroyed the Braamfontein train station in South Africa in 1887. Adsorbents such as diatomaceous earth are part of the mixture that composes this (+) substance and allows for its safe transport. The casualties made possible by this substance inspired its inventor to write (+) awards into his will which are given out in Oslo and Stockholm yearly. For 10 points, name this nitroglycerin-based solid devised by Alfred Nobel, an explosive often packed into \"sticks\"."
      ],
      "answer": "dynamite <MJ> {I}"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A proposed extension of this system in the Vieux Carre (pr. VYUH cah-RAY) area was the subject of a controversy called the \"Second Battle of New Orleans.\" The financial viability of this system was assessed by the Clay Committee. This system was planned in the Yellow Book, and it realized the goals proposed in the Pershing Map. Lady Bird Johnson campaigned for a (20 pts)",
        "\"Beautification Act\" affecting this system. A 1919 army convoy trip and the (10 pts)",
        "Autobahn inspired President Eisenhower to champion the creation of this system. For 10 points, name this system of large roads across the United States."
      ],
      "answer": "interstate highway system <JB> {I} 2015 National History Bowl High School Championships Round 5"
    }
  ]
}